<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Morbus et antidotus = the disease vvith the antidote Or A declaration of Henry Yaxlee of Bouthorpe in the countie of Norfolke Esquire, wherein he sheweth hovv he was a papist, and how by Gods grace he is now lately converted. Published by authoritie.</title>
            <author>Yaxlee, Henry.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15829</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26090</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120544</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855740</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855740</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21242</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15829)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21242)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 946:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Morbus et antidotus = the disease vvith the antidote Or A declaration of Henry Yaxlee of Bouthorpe in the countie of Norfolke Esquire, wherein he sheweth hovv he was a papist, and how by Gods grace he is now lately converted. Published by authoritie.</title>
                  <author>Yaxlee, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 41, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Iones for Nicholas Bourne, and are to be sold at the south entrie of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A papist become a protestant.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Harvard University. Library.</note>
                  <note>Title page mutilated.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anglican converts --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21242:1"/>
            <p>MORBVS ET ANTIDOTVS</p>
            <p>THE DISEASE WITH THE ANTIDOTE OR A Declaration of <hi>Henry Yaxlee</hi> of <hi>Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorpe</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Norfolke</hi> Eſquire, wherein he ſheweth how he was a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, and how by Gods grace he as now lately converte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authoritie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ieremy, 6.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thus ſaith the Lord, ſtand yee in the wayes and ſee, and aske for the old pathes, where is the good way, and walke therein: and ye ſhall find reſt for your ſoules.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Theſſ. 5.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Proue all things, hold faſt that which is good.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by <hi>W. Iones</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at the South Entrie of the Royall Exchange. 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21242:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21242:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vrteous Reader, J craue thy favourable Cenſure vpon what thou ſhalt reade in this booke: What J ſpeake therein of mine owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, is vpon my conſcience true: and what J cite out of Authours, J haue faithfully endevoured to relate truely. If any indeed can advertiſe me of any errour therein, J ſhall thanke him and reforme my ſelfe. Jn one thing I cary ſtill the ſame minde which I did when I was a Papiſt, viz. To haue myne heart (the thing which God moſt deſiereth) alwayes ſtudious to finde, and ready to embrace the true Religion. And I make no doubt, but that God in mercy hath guided me vnto the ſame, and will therein further enlighten and eſtabliſh me vnto my liues end. O that my deare kindred &amp; countrymen would but reade without preiudice, what is ſo plentifully written on either ſide, or
<pb facs="tcp:21242:3"/>be content to heare indifferently what can be pleaded. Then ſhould they clearely ſee, that what auncient truth ſoever the Papiſts doe holde, the Proteſtants alſo doe beleeue and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſame; and that that is all novell, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded and not Catholique, wherein the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant diſſenteth from the Papiſt. But herein is their miſery, they dare not reade, nor ſeeke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny light, but from thoſe whoſe chiefe care is to keep them in darkneſſe, leaſt it ſhould appeare vnto them, that the Proteſtant is truely ſo called, for proteſting againſt the <hi>hay, ſtraw,</hi> and <hi>ſtubble</hi> of the additions and innovations of <hi>Popery</hi> And ſo I reſt in charitie, <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate etiam non ficta,</hi> beſeeching Almighty God that ye may all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, what in his unſpeakable mercy he hath made me.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>The obedient ſonne of my deare Mother the true Church of ENGLAND,</salute>
               <signed>Henry Yaxlee.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21242:3"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION OF <hi>HENRY YAXLEE</hi> OF <hi>BOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THORP</hi> IN THE COVNTY of <hi>Norfolke</hi> Eſquire, wherein he ſheweth how he was a Papiſt, and how by Gods grace he is now lately converted.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Was a Recuſant, becauſe I was taught from my cradle to beleeue the <hi>Catholique Church</hi> by my Creede. And withall I was by all our teachers then perſwaded, that <hi>Rome,</hi> being the ſucceſſiue ſeate of St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> could teach no other, but the true Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Faith, though all other Churches failed.</p>
            <p>But when I found in <hi>Bellarmines</hi> booke
<note n="a" place="margin">De Rom p. lib. 4. cap. 11.</note> that Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> is numbred among thoſe who were condemned by the 7. Councell for Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques. And in <hi>Melch.
<note n="b" place="margin">Lib 6. cap. 1, et vltim.</note> Canus,</hi> that <hi>Celestinus</hi> 3. had decreed, that the woman whoſe husband falleth into hereſie may marie an other. And in <hi>Alfon.
<note n="c" place="margin">Alfonſ <hi>a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ra haere. ſes lib. 1 cap. 4.</note> de Caſt.</hi> that <hi>Omnis homo errare poteſt in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21242:4"/>fide etiamſi Papa ſit. Nam de</hi> Liberio <hi>constat fuiſſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianum, et</hi> Anaſtaſium <hi>Papam fuiſſe Nestorianum.</hi> 1 Every man though he were the Pope him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, may erre in matter of faith, for it is manifeſt that <hi>Liberius</hi> was an <hi>Arrian,</hi> and that Pope <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nastaſius</hi> was a Neſtorian. And in the ſame chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: <hi>Cum conſtet plures eorum eſſe adeo illiteratos vt Grammaticam penitus ignorent, quî fit vt ſacras literas interpretari poſſent? i.</hi> When it is manifeſt that many of them were ſo ignorant, as that they did not at all underſtand the Grammar, how can it be that they ſhould interpret the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures?</p>
            <p>By this I conceived, that it were ſafeſt for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſtian that feareth God, to beleeue the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle according to the Apoſtles C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam,</hi> without addition of <hi>Romanam,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique,</hi> not the Roman Church ſwarving from the Catholique.</p>
            <p>But I was further confirmed, when I found many godly learned and vertuous Prieſts, as <hi>D. Bagſhawe</hi> and Maſter <hi>Iohn Collington,</hi> whoſe names I remember are to their bookes, laying open in their writings, that the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> ſpecially Father <hi>Parſons</hi> haue miſled the Popes to doe the moſt Antichriſtian iniuſtice that ever was heard of to thoſe Prieſts that were appellants to the Popes for juſtice, as you may reade in <hi>Bagſhawes</hi> anſwer and <hi>Collingtons</hi> defence, as alſo in divers other, whereof I giue you this Catalogue. viz. 1. <hi>A letter written by A. C.</hi> 2. <hi>A relation of the faction at Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biche.</hi> 3. <hi>A Dialogue betweene a Secula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rieſt and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21242:4"/>a lay Gentleman.</hi> 4. <hi>Declaratio motuum ac turbatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Angliae.</hi> 5. <hi>Doct. Elies notes. Notes vpon the Apologie.</hi> 6. <hi>Important Conſiderations, written in the name of the Prieſts.</hi> 7. <hi>A ſparing Diſcoverie of Father Parſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Prieſts being Roman Catholickes, doe plainly declare in the ſaid bookes, that the Pope is guided by the violent faction of the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> to do the moſt Antichriſtian injuſtice even to thoſe Prieſtes who tooke a journey to the Pope by the conſent of their brethern by appeale, to lay open the wrongs offered unto them by the <hi>Ieſuites.</hi> Yea Father <hi>Parſons</hi> cauſed them when they were come to <hi>Rome</hi> to be layd in the jaole, where they might haue been ſtarved before ever they had ſpoken with the Pope, if the <hi>French</hi> Kings Embaſſador had not with much difficultie procured them au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, as appeareth in the aforeſaid booke of <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Conſiderations,</hi> written in the name of all the Prieſts diſtreſſed and oppreſſed by the <hi>Ieſuites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereupon, <hi>Collington</hi> in his defence printed 1602. fol. 24. is bould to affirme in capitall let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that Father <hi>Parſons</hi> was ſo notoriouſly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to practiſe treaſon, and to bring an invaſion of Forreiners upon this Realme, as that even <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> ſpeaketh of him in theſe words: <hi>If there be any man that will buy the Kingdome of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>let him repaire to a Merchant in a ſquare blacke capp in this Cittie, and he ſhall haue a very good pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niworth thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in another of the Prieſts books, you ſhall finde, that the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> guide the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21242:5"/>by murthering Kings, Popes and Cardinalls: as in <hi>Quodl.</hi> p. 295.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Ieſuites</hi> and their faction, doe deviſe and publiſh ſuch a kinde of doctrine, <hi>that ſubiects are not bound to obey wicked Princes in their temporall Lawes and commandements, but untill they be able by force of armes to reſiſt him, Quodl. p.</hi> 228. And the qualification being pretended, that though they ſeeke to kill Kings, yet it may be they will ſpare Popes, Cardinals and Biſhops, it is peremptorily anſwered: <hi>Surely no.</hi> ibid. pag. 24. And as there are ſhrewd ſuſpitions in <hi>Rome,</hi> concerning the death of two Popes, two Cardinals and one Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop already, <hi>ſo I make no question at all</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but that hereafter, if any Pope croſſe their plotts and purpoſes, the</hi> Ieſuites <hi>will haue ſuch a figge in ſtore for his Holineſſe, as no Antidote-ſhall prevent or long preſerue his life after it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I had read theſe things in the authours aboue named, I concluded that <hi>Rome</hi> might be a part of the Catholick Church, though a member corrupted with errours, but it could not be the Catholique. Therefore I did not much marvell, when I ſaw diverſe <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſts come openly to Paules Croſſe in <hi>London</hi> and preach, that the <hi>Myſterious working of Antichriſt is now in Rome,</hi> which cauſed them to come out of her as out of <hi>Babilon.</hi> As you may ſee in <hi>Sheldon</hi> the Converts printed Sermon, and in <hi>Higgens</hi> his firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Sermon lately printed. And yet, ſaith <hi>Shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> many Chriſtians may be ſaved in <hi>Rome,</hi> belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the true fundamentall points of Catholique
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21242:5"/>faith and not partaking with her in her latter cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted doctrine, authorized and Printed at <hi>Rome,</hi> which hath beene burnt by the Catholique <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Authoritie in <hi>France,</hi> which I take it are theſe, <hi>Bellarmines</hi> bookes teaching, that the Pope hath power <hi>diſponendi omnium temporalia,</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the temporall things of all.</p>
            <p>And no doubt but this doctrine might cauſe thoſe poore deluded ſoules to enter into the <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der plott,</hi> thinking the deede to be meritorious, as appeared by the ſpeech of Sir <hi>Everad Digh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie</hi> at his death.</p>
            <p>An other may be <hi>Becanus</hi> his booke wherein he diſpuring of King-killing, concludeth in the affirmatiue in theſe wordes, <hi>Nihilcertius,</hi> nothing more certeine. <hi>Suarez</hi> is an other, who in his booke againſt King <hi>Iames,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That none can kill him but thoſe whom the Pope ſhall appoynt.</hi> To theſe may be added <hi>Mariana,</hi> whoſe judgement in his booke is, that <hi>it is the ſafest way to poyſon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe bookes were burnt in <hi>France,</hi> for teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing damnable and ſeditious doctrine, even by the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholique authoritie and partie there. I meane: by ſuch Catholiques as will perſiſt in the true fundamentall poynts of Catholique faith &amp; not be deluded with their errors. No: though the Pope himſelfe ſhould decree them. Much leſſe will they forſake the Apoſtles Creed,
<note place="margin">Extrau. cap v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctam de maior. et obed.</note> 
               <hi>Credo Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam Catholicam,</hi> I beleeue the Catholique Church. Though <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight, hath long ſince Decreed, <hi>That it is alltogether neceſſary to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21242:6"/>to beleeue the Church of Rome,
<note place="margin">See the grand impoſtor of the now Church of Rome, put forth by the Biſh. of <hi>Covent.</hi> &amp; <hi>Leech feild.</hi> 1628.</note> and to be ſubiect to the</hi> Roman <hi>Biſhop.</hi> Which thirteenth Article added by that Pope, the wiſer ſort of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques in <hi>France,</hi> doe not beleeue but oppoſe with wordes, writings, Decrees, and fire; not boaſting themſelves to bee the onely Church inerrant as ROME doth, but holding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be a true member of the Catholique, proteſting againſt theſe corrupted doctrines of <hi>Rome,</hi> innovated by the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> as appeareth by the Prieſts bookes aboue recited, of whom <hi>I</hi> give you here ſome taſte as followeth: ſome whereof I formerly mentioned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct. Elye</hi> in his notes upon the Apologie pag. 9. in the preface ſaith thus: <hi>They plunge themſelues over head and eares in Eccleſiasticall affaires, with ſuch audacitie and obſtinacie as that they haue turned all topſie turvie.</hi> And in the <hi>Quodl.</hi> page 321. We find it thus of the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> doctrine: <hi>Certeinely ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is nothing elſe but fallacie vpon fallacie, error vpon errour, one contradiction encountring another.</hi> And in the booke called <hi>Declar. Mot. ac turb. in Angl. pa.</hi> 29. a <hi>Ieſuite</hi> mainteineth this moſt atheiſticall and heatheniſh aſſertion, that <hi>one who is not a Christian may be</hi> Pope <hi>of Rome.</hi> And as it is in <hi>Anthony Cope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> letter pag 67. an other <hi>Ieſuite</hi> openly and for found doctrine maintayned it firſt to his Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours in the Schoole, and at this inſtant expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> doth ſay: <hi>Non est de fide credere hunc Romanum Pontificem eſſe Christi Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carium.</hi> It is not a matter of Faith to beleeue that this preſent Pope is Chriſts Vicar. Alſo in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21242:6"/>
               <hi>Quodl.</hi> pag 31. Thus we reade: <hi>To let paſſe their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious Doctrine concerning their Generals infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of truth, for deciding of matters. Their abſurd pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxes of Aequivocation.</hi> and ibid. pag 29. <hi>The Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites every way in Printed bookes, in writings &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcripts, and most of all in private conference, have taught contrarie to the Roman Church.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith <hi>Anthony Copely</hi> pag 40. <hi>It is no marvell if in fundamentall poynts of Catholique faith they oppoſe against the Angelicall Doctor, and be therefore endited before his Hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes at this preſent by the</hi> Dominicans <hi>in</hi> Spayne, <hi>for Pelagians and ſundrie other kindes of heretiques; as alſo impoſtors by the</hi> Sorbonites <hi>of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, and all other.</hi> French <hi>Clergie, as we credibly heare.</hi> And <hi>Quodl.</hi> pag 138. <hi>Never was there any Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous order that held ſuch extravagant exorbitant ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reguler opinions as they doe. Doct. Bagſhawes</hi> anſwer pag 20. ſaith thus. <hi>Father Weston and Archer are charged by</hi> Doct. Norden <hi>for defending the ſtues, to be as lawfull as the Pope himſelfe,</hi> as if they had as it ſeemeth, a very league with hell againſt the truth.</p>
            <p>Theſe were not the firſt motiues which made me miſtruſt the <hi>Romiſh</hi> doctrine, for by my bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up I was ſo prejudicate in mine opinion, as that I thought ſcorne to imagine that the <hi>true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique faith,</hi> could infalliblie be received from any place but <hi>Rome.</hi> In ſo much as when I heard of that moſt inhumane barbarous and damnable <hi>Powder plott,</hi> conceived and attempted only by <hi>Romiſh Catholiques,</hi> I was amazed to thinke that from <hi>Rome</hi> and from no other place in the world,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21242:7"/>could be received the ſaving faith. <hi>I</hi> then profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it to certeine famous <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> to whom <hi>I</hi> was then devoted, that <hi>I</hi> thought to beleeue the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholique Church</hi> was as ridiculous, as to ſay <hi>Christendom Kent,</hi> or the <hi>vniverſall particuler.</hi> I was notwithſtanding then eaſily ſatisfied herein, when they told me that the meaning was not to make a particular Church to be vniverſall, but onely to intimate that no faith is truely <hi>Catholick</hi> but that faith which is taught in <hi>Rome,</hi> as they ſayd they were readie to juſtifie, and that there was no more reaſon for vs to forſake the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> for the <hi>Powder plott,</hi> then for the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, to have forſaken Chriſt for the fact of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus I reſted a while ſatisfied,
<note place="margin">Widrintons Supplic. to the Pope</note> untill the oath of Allegiance came out. Then went I to my ſayd Father,
<note n="f" place="margin">Widrint anſ. to <hi>Fits Herb.</hi>
               </note> and told him that diverſe <hi>(e)</hi> Prieſtes defended, that the King had made a lawfull oath, to try the Romiſh which of them did adheare to the true <hi>Catholik</hi> faith of <hi>Rome,</hi> and which to the innovated treaſonable doctrines thereof. And that <hi>(d)</hi> they further defended, that thoſe who refuſed to take this oath, ſhould not onely be hanged for traytors, but looſe alſo their ſoules eternally, for wilfully denying their lawfull Allegiance. Whereupon <hi>I</hi> asked him againe, whether <hi>I</hi> might reade the ſayd bookes to informe and ſatisfie my conſcience, how to carrie my ſelfe betweene my Prince and <hi>Prelate.</hi> His anſwere was, they were hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call bookes, and that <hi>I</hi> ought not to reade them.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21242:7"/>And he further ſaid, that <hi>I</hi> might ſpend my time better in reading <hi>Iohnſons</hi> playes, which he there offered unto me.</p>
            <p>Then and not before I began to diſtruſt, and reading the foreſayd collections in the Authours themſelves, I perceived that all was not found that came from <hi>Rome,</hi> though I was formerly told that the Prieſts had written out of mallice againſt the <hi>Ieſuites:</hi> and not truth.</p>
            <p>Then I conſidered what fundamentall poynts the Proteſtant beleeving <hi>Catholiques,</hi> and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt pretending Catholiques differed in. And <hi>I</hi> found in deverſe proteſtant writters, that they deny not any one poynt of reall <hi>Catholique</hi> Faith explicitely to bee beleeved of neceſſitie, or as neceſſary to ſalvation, as was made evident in the diſputation betweene <hi>Fiſher</hi> and his partner on the <hi>Romiſh</hi> part, and Doctor <hi>White</hi> and Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Feately</hi> for the <hi>Protestants,</hi> in Sir <hi>Humphrie Linne</hi> his houſe in Sheerelane, where the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant diſputantes maintayning, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed no eſſentiall poynt of Catholique Religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, but the innovated unjuſtifiable Doctrine of <hi>Rome.</hi> They made their inſtance. Firſt Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Feately</hi> challenged the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> to ſhew, that for the firſt 500. yeares, any one of fifteene poynts of Popiſh beleefe (which hee then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed had beene beleeved by viſible Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Chriſtians, or by any one Father, or writter of note? Wherewith he droue the <hi>Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> to this ſhamefull evaſion, viz. That theſe are Scholaſticall poyntes, not fundamentall.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21242:8"/>Wherevpon Doctor <hi>White</hi> Replyed, that all thoſe poynes, had been concluded by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of TRENT, and therefore were fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall to the Papiſts. And receiving no anſwer from the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> to this Reply, Doctor <hi>White</hi> inſiſted in ſixe particular poyntes of innovated Popiſh Doctrine, and challenged the Ieſuites to ſhewe if they could, any one Father, or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of note, for the firſt ſixt hundred yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt, who held any one of the ſaid ſixe poynts. Whereto nothing was anſwered, as you may ſee manifeſt in the Relation printed, 1624.</p>
            <p>Since which time, meeting Mr. <hi>Sweete</hi> one of the aforeſayd Ieſuite Diſputants, (<hi>I</hi> asked him, why he would not yeilde as well to trie the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of doctrine as of names, whereas the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Doctrine, and not of names was moſt materiall, to giue ſatisfaction to doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full conſciences, becauſe that by the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, it would have appeared, who had taught according to the Scriptures: Contrary where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, whoſoever teacheth, is accurſed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. But to all this, I could gett no other anſwere, but this, viz. <hi>It would have taken too long a time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I could receiue no better anſwere from Maſter <hi>Sweete, I</hi> immagined that hee might bee of the opinion of the Prieſtes and Papiſtes, in the firſt thirteene yeares of Queene ELIZABETHES Raigne. For the moſt of them did not make then any ſeparation from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21242:8"/>the Proteſtants, as beleeving any reall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene them to cauſe them to ſeparate. For the Laity went to Church generally, and the Prieſts tooke benefices holding the Engliſh Leiturgie as good as the Latine. <hi>Becanus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Controv. Angl. If the King be an hereticke, and command us to pray at the Church with his ſubjects, (poſſumus id praeſtare) wee may doe it.</hi> And I finde ſome other
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Parſons</hi> treat. to mitigat. cap 2. fol. 63.</note> Ieſuites of the ſame opinion, that <hi>Protestants are no heretiques untill that by a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Iudge he or they bee denounced, convicted and condemned by name; which we aſcribe not to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I demaund then, by what rule of charity ſhall the Papiſts ſeparate themſelves from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in the worſhip of God now contrary to the practiſe which was before, 13. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover in the ſame leafe, <hi>Parſons</hi> reaſoneth thus, out of Saint <hi>Auguſtine, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de bapt. cont. Don. c.</hi> 16. <hi>If a man ſhould (for example) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the hereſie of</hi> Photinus, <hi>who denied the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of three perſons in God, and the divinity of Christ, and ſhould thinke it the true Catholicke faith, Iſtum nondum dico haereticum,</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine:</hi>) <hi>I doe not thinke this man yet to be an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retique, except when the doctrine of the Catholique faith (to wit that which hath beene held generally by most Churches in Chriſtendome) be made manifest unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerve here that he doth not ſay the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe that the damnable doctrin which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21242:9"/>brought forth the Powder plot, had been all ready broched and put in practiſe. And the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh bookes burnt in <hi>Paris</hi> for the ſayd doctrine. Elſe hee would have defended the Faith of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niface</hi> the Eight, <hi>That it is alltogether neceſſarie to ſalvation to beleeve the Roman Church.</hi> And ſo let the Article of the APOSTLES CREED be forgotten. For it were needleſſe to enquyre what the Vniverſall Church hath taught if (as that Decree teacheth,) it be ſufficient to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to beleeue the now particular Roman.</p>
            <p>Therefore I beleeve the Romiſh Catholique and Proteſtant Catholique in whatſoever they teach, according to the fundamentall poyntes of the univerſall Faith, contayned in the APO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STLES CREED. And not the corrupted doctrines of the particular Church of Rome, which the Ieſuite Diſputants, were as it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth aſhamed to defend, in Sir <hi>Humphrie Lines</hi> houſe as is aboueſayd.</p>
            <p>Now it may bee demanded how ſo many wiſe, religious, grave and learned Romiſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques, can be thought ſo ignorant, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the particular Roman to be the univerſall Catholique Church, which all are bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue by the Apoſtles Creed.</p>
            <p>It is apparant, that many of them are not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ignorant, or of incapacitie. But it is as apparant that they are made ſo by Arte. For whereas our Saviour Chriſt hath appoynted a preſcribed obedience, according to the Lawes Divine, as in <hi>Deutrenom.</hi> 17.10.11. The vnited
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21242:9"/>Prieſts aforenamed, with the Divines of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> accuſe the now Divines of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Ieſuites; for teaching an abſolute obedience to the Pope, and their Superiour, as I will relate, and beginne with the third part of the Ieſuites Conſtitutions: Cap. 1. Where their vowe of obedience is at large deſcribed as well to the Pope as to their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, in theſe words following. <hi>And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the things which belong to the vowe, &amp;c. we will ſpeake of obedience which all must labour ſtrictly to obſerve; and not onely in thoſe things which they are bound, but others alſo, though the ſame be not a commandement but onely a ſigne of their Superiours will, as if it were our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Christs owne voice. And let every one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade himſelfe to be governed even like a dead carkaſſe turned and tumbled even which way ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a man will. Or like an olde mans ſtaffe which ſerveth him that holdeth it in his hand for whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he will uſe it where and when he liſt.</hi> Vpon this paſſage the Gloſſe hath theſe words: <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, concerning the execution of it, is then performed when that which is commanded is done.</hi> The two which diſpatched the two <hi>Henries</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> ſeemed to have learned this Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: And if the powder had taken fire, more had become proficient in this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>Now it appeareth what this new doctrine hath done in matters of fact: ſo it is alſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21242:10"/>too manifeſt how it worketh upon faith and beleefe. For hereby they are made careleſſe what or how they doe beleeve. For they muſt not ſearch or know whether the Romiſh Church doth teach the Catholicke faith or no; but they muſt beleeve it as it were by an Attorney, becauſe the Ieſuites ſay ſo, and tell them that <hi>Boniface</hi> hath decreed it: and that they muſt give accompt for their ſoules: So that the people neede take no further care. Whereby many Romane Catholickes take their liberty to frequent tavernes and worſe matters which I could name (but that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and modeſty doth reſtraine) and yet thinke that upon the Satturday ſhrift they ſhall be cleared of all by the Prieſts abſolution. For ſo long as they beleeve as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> beleeveth, (whether that beleefe be true or falſe) they are confident that the Prieſt muſt give account for their ſoules. And this is the new doctrine, and holy obedience taught by the Ieſuites.</p>
            <p>But leaſt any one ſhould thinke that I ſlander them, I will cite <hi>Peter Maffe</hi> a Prieſt of their Society, in a booke by him written of the life of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> with the approbation of their Generall <hi>Aquauiua, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. Where hee calleth the aforeſaid obedience, <hi>Sapientem hanc ſanctamque ſtultitiam caecae obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae: This wiſe and holy folly of blinde obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:21242:10"/>
            <p>Hee that will, may reade more hereof, <hi>cap.</hi> 17. and 18. of the ſecond booke of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites Catechiſme printed 1602 by the united Prieſts of France and England, as appeareth in the Epiſtle of the Engliſh Prieſts prefixed with this title: <hi>The ſecular Prieſts Preface to the Engliſh Catholiques.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that all may the more fully underſtand how unreaſonable a thing this blinde obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is, I will here produce ſome paſſages out of the writings of that late famous Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher <hi>Charroun</hi> a Romiſh Prieſt, and a Doctour of the Civill Law in <hi>Paris,</hi> as I am infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, (of whom I have heard high commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations from Maſter <hi>Martin</hi> the Ieſuite for his ſanctity of life and for his learning) who in his booke of wiſedome, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. hath divers paſſages of ſpeciall uſe in this point: as Sect. 1. <hi>To judge is to examine and weigh the reaſons and counter-reaſons on all parts, the weight and merit of them, and thereby worke out the truth.</hi> And in the ſame page he teacheth, <hi>That a man ſhould holde himſelfe alwayes ready to entertaine better if it appeare. Yea not to be offended if ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall conteſt with him againſt that hee thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth better if it appeare. Yea not to be offended if another ſhall contest with him against that which he thinketh better, but rather deſire to heare what may be ſaid.</hi> And in the next page in the ſame ſect. <hi>But I ſee and perceive a ſort of people glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous affirmative, which would rule the world, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21242:11"/>command as it were with a rod, and as others in former times have ſworne to certaine principles, and married themſelves to certaine opinions, ſo they would that all others ſhould doe the like, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they oppoſe themſelves to this noble liberty of the Spirit.</hi> And then in the next ſect. <hi>To judge of all is the property of a wiſe and ſpirituall man. Spiritualis omnia dijudicat, &amp; à nemine judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: The ſpirituall man judgeth all things, and is judged of none.</hi> And is not this ſutable to the Scriptures which are the unerring word of almighty God; which ſaith, <hi>Beleeve not every Spirit, but try the Spirits, Becauſe many falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets are gone into the world?</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Search the Scriptures, Ioh.</hi> 5 39.</p>
            <p>But to returne to the words of Maſter <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roune:</hi> Thus it followeth, <hi>The true office of a man, his moſt proper and naturall exerciſe, his worthieſt profeſſion is to judge. Why is a man diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing, reaſoning, understanding? Why hath he a ſpirit? to build castles in the ayre? to feed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with fooleries and vanities as the greatest part of the world doth? Quis unquam oculos tenebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cauſa habuit? Why have men eyes but to ſee withall? Doubtleſſe to underſtand, to judge of all things. And therefore is he called the governor, the ſuperintendent, the keeper of nature, of the world, of the workes of God. To goe about to deprive him of this right is to make him no more a man but a beast.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And a little further he procedeth thus: <hi>It
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21242:11"/>is then ſtrange that ſo many men who either are or make ſhew of underſtanding and ſufficiency, depriue themſelves willingly of this right and authority: So naturall, ſo juſt and excellent, who without the examining or judging of any thing, receive and approove whatſoever is preſented, either becauſe it hath a faire ſemblance, or becauſe it is in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, credit and practiſe. Yea they thinke that it is not lawfull to examine or doubt of any thing, in ſuch ſort doe they debaſe and degrade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. They are forward in other things and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, but in this they are fearefull and ſubmiſſe, though it doe justly appertaine unto them, and with ſo much reaſon. Seeing there are a thouſand lyes for one truth, a thouſand opinions of one and the ſame thing, and but one true, why ſhould not I examine with the inſtrument of reaſon which is the truer, the more reaſonable, honeſt and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table? Goe to then, the wiſe man ſhall judge of all, nothing ſhall eſcape him which hee bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not to the barre and to the ballance. It is to play the part of prophane men and beaſts, to ſuffer themſelves to bee ledde like oxen. What can a wiſe man have above a prophane, if hee muſt have his ſpirit, his minde, his principall and heroicall part a ſlave? It is an hard thing to bridle the libertie of the ſpirit, and if a man would doe it, it is the greateſt tyranny that may be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I can by no meanes beleeve that <hi>Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vare intellectum in re fidei, to captivate the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21242:12"/>in the matter of faith,</hi> belongeth abſolutely unto any but unto God alone, and unto man conditionally, <hi>viz. Cùm docue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint juxta legem,</hi> when their doctrine is ſutable unto Gods word.</p>
            <p>But as you have ſeene how the learned <hi>Charoun</hi> doth condemne and confute that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked doctrine of blinde obedience; ſo I will alſo adde his cenſure upon the effects and practiſes which that Doctrine produceth: For in the ſame booke, cap. 5. ſect. 28. thus I reade: <hi>What execrable wickedneſſe hath the zeale of religion brought forth? Is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſubject or occaſion that hath yeelded the like?</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tantum Relligio potuit ſuadere malorum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quae peperit ſaepè ſceleroſa atque impia facta:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Religion workes ſo farre in evill men,</l>
               <l>As wicked deedes it acteth now and then.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Not to love him, yea to looke upon him with a wicked eye, as upon a monſter that beleeveth not as hee beleeveth; To thinke to be polluted by ſpeaking or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing with him, is one of the ſweeteſt and moſt pleaſing actions of theſe kinde of people. Hee that is an honeſt man by ſcruple, and a religious bridle take heede of him, and account of him as hee is and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21242:12"/>hee hath religion without honeſtie, I will not ſay hee is more wicked, but farre more dangerous than hee that hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one nor the other. Who ſo kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth you, will thinke that hee doth an acceptable ſervice unto God: Not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe religion teacheth or any way fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth wickedneſſe, as ſome very foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly and maliciouſly from this place doe object, (for the moſt abſurd and falſeſt religion doth it not,) but the reaſon is, that having no taſte, nor image, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of honeſty but by imitation and for the ſervice of religion, and thinking that to be an honeſt man is no other thing than to be carefull to advance religion: They beleeve all things whatſoever, be it trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, treachery, ſedition, rebellion, or any other offence, to bee not onely lawfull and ſufferable, being coloured with zeale and the care of religion, but alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, meritorious, and worthy ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonization, if it ſeeme for the progreſſe and advancement of religion, and the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of their adverſaries.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you may ſee what conceit that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man had of yeelding to men that abſolute obedience which is due to God alone. So that he was farre from the doctrine of the Ieſuites, who in their 13 rule do teach that if the Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour ſay that white is black, we muſt beleeve
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21242:13"/>it and obey. And a Ieſuite once avowed to my face before ſufficient witneſſe, that this rule is orthodoxe.</p>
            <p>Hee that will ſee more concerning this point, let him reade <hi>De la Mar.</hi> againſt the Ieſuites, his open pleading in Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> againſt <hi>Monthalon,</hi> their choſen Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate. He that would beholde how the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath beene led by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular factions to forſake the univerſall Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke faith, let him reade <hi>George Carleton</hi> ſince Biſhop of <hi>Chichester</hi> his booke of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction Regall, Papall, Epiſcopall: If any man reade theſe and ſee not the univerſall faith there brought to particular fancie, it muſt bee <hi>craſſa ignorantia,</hi> if hee have will to pleaſe God, and capacity for to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</p>
            <p>But the greateſt motives yet to perſwade me that Rome hath corrupted the Catholique faith, are two: The firſt is for that all the moſt religious, the moſt learned, yea the very Canonized Saints of <hi>Rome</hi> have in all latter ages cryed out of the corruptions in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as you may finde in a booke publiſhed both in Latine and in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh by IAMES MAXVVELL a Reſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of Antiquities, which no Romiſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt ever contradicting, I preſume that it cannot bee excepted againſt by the later yeares.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21242:13"/>
            <p>See what the Prieſts haue written againſt the Ieſuites. He that hath not meanes to come by the bookes themſelues, may reade the Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions made by <hi>Tho. Iames,</hi> which I haue found truely cited out of the ſaid books of the Prieſts. The <hi>Collections of Tho. Iames printed at Oxford,</hi> were ſold by <hi>Iohn Barnes</hi> neere <hi>Holborne</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duite.</p>
            <p>The ſecond motiue is, that within this later hundred yeeres, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped authority to expurge, reprint, alter or change, what they haue thought good, out of both ancient and late Writers that ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, as may appeare by their <hi>Indices Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgatorij,</hi> concerning which, I referre you to D. <hi>Iames</hi> his Collections printed, 1625.</p>
            <p>But concerning the credit of the Canonized Saints, and others cited by <hi>Maxwell,</hi> it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary you ſhould heare what the greateſt and learnedſt Doctors of <hi>Rome</hi> haue thought of them. Thus may you reade in <hi>Trithem: Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas,</hi> in his booke of illuſtrious men, <hi>That Pope Eugenius the third, with the conſent of</hi> 18 <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, and a great number of Biſhops aſſembled in the Councell of Treiur. And alſo Pope Boniface the ninth, did Canonize diners of the Saints that ſpake againſt the corruptions of</hi> Rome. <hi>Turrecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata, Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Baronius,</hi> with the moſt famous learned men of <hi>Rome,</hi> haue all highly commended the ſaid Saints, that thus cryed out of <hi>Rome,</hi> and called out loud for reformation in their dayes. The like was done by the good
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21242:14"/>
               <hi>French</hi> Cardinall, <hi>Peter de Aliaco,</hi> in his booke of Reformation of the Church, in his time preſented to the Councell of <hi>Conſtance;</hi> And the Councels both of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Baſil,</hi> did <hi>vna voce,</hi> diſallow the Popes vſurpation, in challenging himſelfe to be aboue a generall Councell, inſomuch that the ſaid Councell de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered it as a depoſite of the Church by vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous conſent, in forme of a Decree, that it ought not to be ſo. In theſe words, <hi>The Pope (tenetur obedire) ought</hi> (or is bound) <hi>to obey the Councell (etiam in fide &amp; moribus) euen in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of FAITH and manners.</hi> Yea, where was the Popes authority aboue a generall Councel, when all Appeales to parts beyond the Seas, were prohibited by the <hi>African</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell.</p>
            <p>They are not then the late Proteſtants alone that haue called for Reformation of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, but euen alſo theſe ancient. The late famous Sir <hi>Thomas Moore,</hi> holden one of the lights of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and defender thereof in his time, ſeemeth to ſcorne that any man ſhould beleeue that he was ſo farre corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Faith, as to beleeue the Pope to be aboue a generall Councell.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dial. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 26.</note> His words are, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer did I beleeue the Pope to bee aboue a generall Councell.</hi> Notwithſtanding the Papalins, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Catholicke faith, haue accounted the <hi>French</hi> Church to bee a ſchiſmaticall Church for holding the Vniuerſall or generall Councell to be aboue the Pope, as appeareth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21242:14"/>at large, in the aforeſaid pleadings of <hi>De la Martilire,</hi> againſt the Ieſuites.</p>
            <p>Heare now what the Seminarie Prieſts ſpeake againſt the faction of the Ieſuites, that hath ſwayed and ouer-ruled <hi>Rome,</hi> at and ſince the Councell of <hi>Trent. Watſon, Quodl. pag.</hi> 82. doubteth that Antichriſt may be already come, for that the Ieſuites be the fore-runners of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, though it appeareth that Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> thought he was come before, when as he ſaith, <hi>Ep.</hi> 127. that <hi>Antichrist then ſate in S.</hi> Peters <hi>chaire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then the godlieſt and learnedſt of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> haue in all Ages, cryed out of the corruptions, both of the doctrine and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as you may ſee in the books aforeſaid, then we may ſay there haue neuer wanted Profeſſors and Proteſtants in all Ages, defending that Catholicke <hi>Roman</hi> Faith, which <hi>Paul</hi> commended to the <hi>Romans,</hi> reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the tyranous, vſurped, innouated Doctrine of the Church or Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> as may bee further ſeene in that from time to time, euen ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councels, as well as Prouinciall, haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſted the innouations of <hi>Rome.</hi> The <hi>African</hi> Councell, and others of that time reſiſted Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales to the Pope. The later Councels of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> and <hi>Baſil,</hi> haue concluded that the Pope is not aboue a Generall Councell.</p>
            <p>As then Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that God hath ſet in the Church Apoſtles, Prophets, Euangeliſts, Teachers, for the perfecting of the Faith, <hi>vntill
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21242:15"/>all come to the vnity of the Faith, Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13.
<note place="margin">See Maſter <hi>Bernards</hi> booke entituled, <hi>looke beyond</hi> Luther.</note> And that vn till <hi>Chriſts comming againe,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.14. So if you looke beyond <hi>Luther,</hi> you ſhall finde that there neuer wanted a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble company of Paſtors proteſting againſt the innovated doctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which made, as I ſuppoſe, the Ieſuite diſputants in Sir <hi>Humphrey Linds</hi> his houſe aſhamed to try the ſucceſsion of doctrine, offering their blinde buttery booke of names. For if they durſt try their ſucceſsion of their doctrine; Why did they not either then vndertake it, or ſince make ſupplication to his Maieſty, that they might proue the ſame, and ſo ſaue their Credits.</p>
            <p>And ſince that I had digeſted and ſet downe in writing theſe former inducements, I haue beene yet further confirmed by the reading of two bookes, the one of Sir <hi>Humphrey Linds,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>via tuta,</hi> wherein is manifeſtly proued that whatſoeuer the Proteſtants hold poſitiuely for matter of faith, no learned Papiſts, can or euer could deny. And that whatſoeuer the Proteſtants deny of the things held by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, the ſame cannot be prooued to be Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke and Apoſtolicke, agreeing with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed.</p>
            <p>The other is Doctor <hi>Fauours</hi> booke, entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Antiquity triumphing ouer Nouelties;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is as plainely proued that the Papiſts doe ſpeake contemptuouſly and diſgracefully of the Scriptures, to deterre men from reading of them. Contemne thoſe firſt and beſt generall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21242:15"/>Councels wherin they ſpeake againſt them, and for the Proteſtants. And in the later, they take what parts make for them, and reiect what makes againſt them, as reprobate; as I find Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Bellarmines</hi> diſtinction of them to bee <hi>partim probata, partim reprobata.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. &amp; eccl.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>The like doe they by the Fathers, and alſo by Hiſtories, as you may ſee, if you reade, <hi>cap.</hi> 7, 8, 9. of the ſaid booke of D. <hi>Fauour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all this it ſeemeth will not ſerue the turne, for they haue ſet vp ſhops and Inquiſitors of purpoſe, called their <hi>Indices Expurgatorij,</hi> to blot out in the Catholicke Writers, what makes againſt them, with a <hi>deleatur,</hi> and to adde what may ſerue their turne. And likewiſe in their citations they make vſe of Baſtard and counterfeit Fathers acknowledged by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be ſuch, as you may ſee more plainly and particularly in Doctor <hi>Iames</hi> his booke prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, 1612. entituled, <hi>A Treatiſe of Scripture, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, Fathers, corrupted by the Romiſh Paſtors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for their contempt of the Fathers: When <hi>Tertullian</hi> pleaſeth <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> he is with him, <hi>graniſsimus Author,</hi> A moſt graue Author, a famous Doctor, a Catholike Writer. <hi>Bellar. de Rom. pont. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5. But if he ſpeake againſt, or pleaſe not <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> then he is an Heretique, and he will anſwer, <hi>fidem non eſſe omnino adhiben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Tertulliano in hac parte,</hi> that no credite at all is to be giuen to <hi>Tertullian</hi> in this caſe, <hi>ibid. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>And as for the vſe which the Papiſts doe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21242:16"/>afford vnto that euidence of antiquity, which is hiſtories; Doctor <hi>Fauour</hi> propoſeth cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine examples to make it plaine, that in this caſe the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> either miſerably or dogged<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſnarle at all antiquity, or vtterly <hi>reiect and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. § 20.</note> the moſt expedite courſe they can deuiſe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow, that which in truth would ouerthrow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His firſt inſtance is in the matter of Pope <hi>Ione.</hi> The truth of which hiſtorie, when he hath confirmed by the witneſſe of <hi>more then a double Grand-iurie of ſufficient Authors older and later, Greekes and Latines, domeſticall and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, Diuines, Lawyers, and Phyſitians, Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, Poets, and other humanitians, Prieſts, Biſhops, (in their accompt Saints) and Cardinals, Fryars, Monkes and Canons, yea, and whole Vniuerſities, not one of them an enemy: nay, not ſo much as one of them not a friend to the Roman Catholicke Court and Religion, &amp;c.</hi> At laſt (hauing named the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Authors in the Margin of his page) hee ſaith; <hi>Yet becauſe this ſtory doth preiudice the vaunt of their perpetuall ſucceſsion, doth make vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine their pretended onely ſufficient ordination, giues a ſhrewd ſhake to their counterfeit rocke, &amp;c. Fiue or ſixe and thirty Authors conſtantly in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers countries, in many Ages, in Catholicke Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerſities. Citizens of</hi> Rome, <hi>and Officers in the Popes Court, ſecular &amp; religious, are all corrupted, falſified, denyed, diſcredited, ſhaken off and branded with infamy, and all muſt be without ſap or ſenſe, truth or honeſty, learning or credit, onely to ſalue
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21242:16"/>that frothy Sea from this filthy Queane. And all this begun and ſet on foot by that one conſcience<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe</hi> Onuphrius,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Rom. pon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>whom Cardinall</hi> Bellarmine <hi>himſelfe reiecteth as a contradictor of all antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and for auouching that for which he hath no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</hi> Who was borne ſome hundreds of yeares after ſome of the ſaid Hiſtorians, which is ſtrange that any man ſhould beleeue it fit, that he alone is ſufficient to out-beard, and out-face all former antiquity. <hi>And</hi> (ſaith D. <hi>Fauour) I maruell how they laugh not one at another, when they ſee how they gull the ſimple world, as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſpices did among the</hi> Gentiles.</p>
            <p>His ſecond example is the ſtory of Pope <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſter,</hi> the ſecond, infeofing Antichriſt in the Sea of <hi>Rome, by liucrie and ſeiſin,</hi> about which he ſheweth that they vſe the like dealing, as about the former ſtory of Pope <hi>Ione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And while I conſidered theſe foule abuſes in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> there came to my minde an anſwer which a Ieſuite, Father <hi>Floyd</hi> made vnto me, when I told him that King <hi>Iames</hi> his anſwer to Cardinall <hi>Perrone</hi> his ſpeech in the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> did charge the ſaid Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall with manifold falſifications of the holy Scriptures, to proue the Popes power to depoſe Princes. And that if the King were not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, the cauſe would be much ſcandalized. The Ieſuite anſwered mee, that there was too much written already, and that he muſt be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered another way. I was afraid then to aske him any more, fearing it might be another
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21242:17"/>Powder-plot, the rather becauſe I heard Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Smith,</hi> my old Lady <hi>Kneuets</hi> Prieſt, affirme, that he had heard a zealous Catholicke ſay, when he firſt heard how the Powder-plot had miſſed, that it was the onely way in the world that could haue beene deuiſed to haue rooted out the Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>And now I am eaſily drawne to beleeue Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Floyd,</hi> that they will anſwer no more with bookes or writings, but with force and plots, if as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Ex ore tuo te iudico,</hi> a man may iudge according to their owne words, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if we conſider how the ſecular Prieſts do charge the Ieſuites with ambitious vſurping authority in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> corrupting it with their treaſonable doctrines, as is euident in the ſaid Prieſts bookes, whereof I haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy giuen the Reader ſome taſte. And I thinke good here to adde more, the rather becauſe that the bookes are not eaſily to be had, for that the Ieſuites making vſe of a rich <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ladies purſe, for the buying vp and burning of hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call bookes, they tooke vp as many as they could of theſe Prieſts books, which they coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worſt of all.</p>
            <p>This Lady was by the Ieſuites placed in <hi>Barbican,</hi> neere to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſadours houſe, and being apprehended by a Purſeuant, ſhe was committed to priſon, where hauing continued, ſhee thought her ſelfe therein moſt happy, for that as the Papiſts commonly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, ſhe had come from <hi>Spaine</hi> hither, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21242:17"/>to endure ſome afflictions with the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Papiſts for the Catholicke cauſe.</p>
            <p>But to returne to my purpoſe of relating ſome paſſages out of the Prieſts bookes, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Ieſuites.
<note n="a" place="margin">Dialogue betweene a ſecular Prieſt and a lay <hi>Cath. p,</hi> 86.</note> 
               <hi>They are indeed Prieſts, but exceeding cunning politickes withall. And theſe
<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>D. Bagſh. anſ. p.</hi> 10.</note> politique Canuaſers, or Machiauellian
<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quodl. p.</hi> 15.</note> polititi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, haue
<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ib. b. p.</hi> 147.</note> ſo many Machiaucllian deuices, as euery plot and drift ſeemeth to be an infallible rule of falſehood, and principle in chiefe, whereby the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites doe ſquare their actions as, neuer a Prince in Chriſtendome, nor any man liuing can tell where to find, or how to trace and truſt them,
<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quodl. p.</hi> 17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21.</note> for in all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious and temporizing platformes,
<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid p.</hi> 18.</note> atheall plots of perdition,
<note n="g" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Machiauellian, or rather Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humetan-like faction,
<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 62.</note> Heatheniſh, tyrannicall, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanicall and Turkiſh gouernment, none
<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Jbid. p</hi> 64.</note> goeth beyond the Ieſuites at this day.
<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 62.</note> And they are able to ſet</hi> Aretine, Lucian, Machiauell, <hi>yea, and</hi> Don Lucifer <hi>to ſchoole, as impoſsible for him by all the Art he hath to beſot men as they doe;</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their blind, dead, carkaſſe obedience, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly expreſſed out of <hi>Maffeus,</hi> and the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites Conſtitutions.</p>
            <p>But to proceed with ſome further paſſages of the bookes before mentioned.
<note n="l" place="margin">Relation of the faction at <hi>Wisb. p.</hi> 77.</note> 
               <hi>It is to bee feared leſt they will bring in bondage, not onely Prelates, but the very Princes and Monarches themſelues.
<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quodl p.</hi> 173.</note> They haue houlſtered, hearded, and borne-out, many foule matters againſt the greateſt and chiefeſt Princes on earth.
<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Declar. mot. ac turb in Angl. p.</hi> 17.</note> They haue plotted diuers forraigne inuaſions.
<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. p</hi> 83.</note> They ſet Kingdomes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21242:18"/>to ſale, and talke and write of nothing but forraigne enemies that ſhall inuade this Land;
<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quodl p.</hi> 186.</note> So that this Land by their miſchieuous drifts and deuiſes, lies o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to the ſpoyle of the firſt that can catch it.
<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>ibid p.</hi> 182.</note> They fiſh for a Monarchy,
<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>ibid p.</hi> 324.</note> and haue at all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for both eſtate Eccleſiaſticall and Temporall. But
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rel.</hi> of the fact at <hi>Wish. p.</hi> 71.</note> ſpecially they challenge a ſpirituall Monarchy ouer all</hi> England <hi>by
<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid p.</hi> 74.</note> right or wrong ſeeking it. So
<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>odl. p.</hi> 234</note> that all the Ieſuites ayme at one marke, and one courſe, and conceiue one and the ſame generall hope to haue</hi> England <hi>a</hi> Iaponian <hi>Monarchy (as one termed it) or an apiſh Iland of Ieſuites.
<note n="w" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quodl. p.</hi> 65.</note> They haue intelligence in all the Kings Courts in Europe, by ſome principall man or woman of marke of their placing.
<note n="x" place="margin">Jbid.</note> And their chiefe agent to diſcouer the ſecrets of Princes, is alwayes a Ieſuite in</hi> re <hi>or in</hi> ſpe.
<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 315.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe Agents in all Princes Courts, giue informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their Generall once a moneth: So that
<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 65.</note> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is done in</hi> England, <hi>but it is knowne in</hi> Rome <hi>within a moneth after at the least.
<note n="a" place="margin">Elies notes. <hi>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 34.</note> They ſeeke to haue all men at their beeke and commandment. And
<note n="b" place="margin">Relation of the faction at <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>b p.</hi> 69.</note> ſo miſerable is the ſtate of the Catholickes in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>that all muſt depend vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                           <desc>…</desc>
                        </gap> p.</hi> 9.</note> as though the fee-ſimple of all mens acts, words, and thoughts, were in their gift. And therefore of all orders, the
<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Jbid. p.</hi> 24.</note> Capuchins liue beſt with the Ieſuites, becauſe the Ieſuites would willingly haue all, and the Capuchins would willingly haue nothing, but euen to keepe life and ſoule together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any body wanting the Authors here cited would ſee more to this effect, he may be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Doctor <hi>Iames</hi> his booke of the <hi>Downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21242:18"/>of Ieſuites,</hi> whoſe Collections I haue exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and haue found to be true as I ſaid before.</p>
            <p>If then the Prieſts accuſe the Ieſuites (who are now the onely rulers of Popes, Princes, and Prieſts lippes, more for feare of them, then for any affection vnto them) to be meere hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Machiauelian Atheiſts, how can a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an man that feareth God, beleeue ſuch a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church guided (as their owne Prieſts confeſſe, ſo abundantly) by ſuch a particular fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to be the Catholicke Church, and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the myſtery of iniquity. Seeing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith,
<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.</note> that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man of ſinne <hi>oppoſeth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth himſelfe aboue all that is called God, ſitting in the Temple of God, as God.</hi> And that the <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of iniquity doth worke, and that the comming of that wicked, is after the working of Sathan with all power and ſignes, and lying wonders, and with all deceiueableneſſe of vnrighteouſneſse in them that periſh, becauſe they receiued not the loue of the truth. To whom God ſhall ſend ſtrong deluſions, that they ſhall beleeue a lye.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 4. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And ſeeing that Saint <hi>Gregory,</hi> foretelling of theſe times, ſaith, <hi>The king of pride is at hand, an army of Prieſts is prepared to attend him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which are moſt true of the Pope, and of the enchanting ſubtilties of the Ieſuites, hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winking the world with blindneſſe, as is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by their owne brethren and Prieſts.</p>
            <p>Whereunto to we may adde the iudicious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe lately made to the <hi>Polonian</hi> Nobility, aſſembled in Parliament, for reformation,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21242:19"/>
               <hi>Vide Mercur. Gallo-Belgic. Dantiſc. Anno</hi> 1607. <hi>p.</hi> 67, <hi>&amp; deinceps:</hi> Where it is anowed, that the greateſt enemies to that and other free eſtates, were Ieſuites, &amp;c. and that their faction is a moſt agill ſharpe ſword, whoſe blade is ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed at pleaſure in the bowels of euery Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, but the Handle reacheth to <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Spaine.</hi> So that the very life, death, and fortunes of all, Kings, Magiſtrates, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealthes, hang vpon the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> of the Ieſuites pleaſures.</p>
            <p>I cannot be of the mind of ſome of my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, yet <hi>Romiſh</hi> Catholiques, who late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly told me, that they muſt needes be Atheiſts, if they forſake the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe they cannot tell forſooth, where the Proteſtant ſucceſſion of Prieſthood and Doctrine, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Luthers</hi> dayes. But I ſay, that if they were not holden ſtrongly with their dead carkaſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the Ieſuites, and their thirteenth rule afore deciphered, they might well ſee that the Proteſtants in <hi>England,</hi> can proue vndeny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, the lawfull ſucceſsion of Prieſthood, euen from the Popiſh Doctrines and their Records, when as <hi>Luther</hi> firſt ſought the Reformation. If then the Popiſh bee good, the Proteſtants muſt be good alſo, as appeareth by Maſter <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> booke of this argument. And that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Proteſtants is Catholicke, no Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt can be ſo impudent, as to deny, if hee will pull off the Popes ſpectacles, clouded with the miſt of the Ieſuites thirteenth rule. For as I
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21242:19"/>ſhewed before, the Proteſtants teach no do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in the affirmatiue, but what the Papiſts hold at this day, <hi>viz.</hi> the Apoſtles Creede, and that according to the ancient Catholicke inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the <hi>Nicen</hi> and <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creeds, and the firſt foure generall Councels.</p>
            <p>They deny indeed the Popiſh addition of 12 other articles made by Pope <hi>Pius quartus:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Papiſts cannot proue any one of them Catholicke and Apoſtolicke: And becauſe the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>If wee,
<note place="margin">Cal. 1.8.</note> or an Angell from heauen teach otherwiſe, let him be accurſed.</hi> Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſaith of the Apoſtles Creed, <hi>He that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth more, beleeueth too much, and he that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth leſſe, beleeueth too little.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The famous learned Friar <hi>Padro Paulo</hi> of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> in his Hiſtory of the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> which confirmed that Creed of <hi>Pius quartus;</hi> diſcouereth how that Counſell was ouer-ruled by the faction of the Ieſuites, and that it was there a common by-word, euen among the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts themſelues, that that Councell was gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>by the holy Ghoſt, which came euery weeke from</hi> Rome <hi>in a Cloakebagge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we may not beleeue an Angell of light, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching otherwiſe then the Apoſtles Creed, then blame not the Proteſtants proteſting againſt the Papiſts late additions, and corruptions, but rather beleeue and follow them, becauſe they teach nothing but that which the Papiſts themſelues cannot deny to bee the Catholicke faith. And deny ſuch a Councell, ſuch a Creed,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21242:20"/>ſo new, and ſo branded by the Papiſts owne beſt and moſt learned Prieſts.</p>
            <p>Mine old acquaintance propoundeth to me yet another queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> How good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans could conuerſe and communicate with ſuch a Church, ſo corrupted before <hi>Luther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is lately well anſwered by the Biſhop of <hi>Exeter,</hi> in his booke, entituled, <hi>The old Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and well proſecuted by others, who make it plaine that one may communicate, as they did with the Papiſts, as wee may communicate with the Diuell, when he ſaid, <hi>Thou art Chriſt, the Sonne of the euerliuing God.</hi> Not becauſe the Diuell ſpake it, but becauſe it is Gods truth, and conſequently ours. So we may communicate in the truth with any, in errour with none. For example, Some Prieſts were as vehemently ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and zealous denyers of <hi>Romes</hi> corrupted doctrine before <hi>Luthers</hi> time, as Maſter <hi>Burton</hi> and others now. And many then reſiſted the <hi>Roman</hi> errors, euen to death, as the <hi>Wiclifians</hi> and other learned and religious Prieſts, as the Hiſtories of the ſeuerall times and ages doe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie. Others more cooley and aduiſedly ſought the Reformation, as <hi>Eraſmus, Caſſaender, Petrus de Aliaco,</hi> and others, who communicated with <hi>Rome</hi> in her truthes, and ſcorned her errours, as appeareth by their bookes written to men, and to Councels, to reforme the Church, euen ſo long before <hi>Luthers</hi> dayes, as the Councell of <hi>Conſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be obiected, why then ſhould the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21242:20"/>now proteſt a ſeparation, more then the ſaid Reformers did before <hi>Luther?</hi> This is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fficiently anſwered in the diſpute between M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Burton</hi> and his Antagoniſts, where Maſter <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> (though accounted an ouer-zealous Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) confeſſeth that they were not bound then, and yet are bound now ſince the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> to ſeparate. Becauſe that ſince, &amp; by the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> men are <hi>ſub anathemate,</hi> bound to beleeue, as well the errours as the truthes of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and as well the new Creed of <hi>Pius quartus,</hi> as the ancient Creed of the Apoſtles. Before the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> &amp; publication of theſe new Articles, men would ordinarily ſay, when this new teaching was diſcouered, <hi>Let them pipe what they will, wee will dance what wee liſt;</hi> Meaning, that they thought themſelues ſafe if they beleeued the old Creed, and left the new <hi>Romiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I ſay further in the words of a learned Diuine;
<note place="margin">In his Treatiſe of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Faith.</note> that though we could then communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with ſuch a Church without euident dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of damnation (as they did then) yet in as much as we cannot communicate with it now vpon any better termes then legall ſeruants or bondſlaues do with their Maſters, we are bound in conſcience and religious diſcretion, when lawfull occaſion is offered (as now it is) to vſe our liberty, to ſeeke our freedome, rather then to liue in bondage, according to the rule of the Apoſtle giuen to ſeruants, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.20, 21. <hi>&amp;c.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21242:21"/>Let euery man abide in the ſame Calling wherein he is called. Art thou called being a ſeruant? care not for it. But if thou maiſt be made free, vſe it rather, for he that is called in the Lord, being a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, is the Lords freeman. Likewiſe alſo he that is called, being free, it Chriſts ſeruant. Yee are bought with a price, be yee not the ſeruants of men;</hi> that is, yeeld not that abſolute obedience to men (as the Ieſuites teach) which is due onely to God.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Padr. Paul.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the State of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice.</hi>
               </note> That obedience (as the learned <hi>Venetian</hi> ſaith) which God commands vs to performe to our Eccleſiaſticall ſuperiors, is not a fooliſh or ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous ſubiection, nor is the power of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late an arbitrary iudgement, but both the one and the other muſt be ruled by the Word of God, according to the place, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. before cited. Abſolute obedience is due onely to God, and whoſoeuer ſuppoſeth any humane will to be infallible, vttereth great blaſphemy in aſcribing that to the creature, which is due onely to the Creator.</p>
            <p>I once asked a learned <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſt within this ſeuen yeeres, whether praying to Saints were a matter of Faith or not. He anſwered that wee are not bound to pray to Saints. So ſhall you finde many <hi>Romiſh</hi> Catholickes before <hi>Luthers</hi> dayes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſponſ. ad apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiam Card. Bell. p.</hi> 9.</note> and after the Councell of <hi>Lateran,</hi> who would ſay at the Eleuation, <hi>Adoro te ſi tu es Christus, i.e.</hi> If thou be Chriſt, I doe adore or worſhip thee. So farre were the wiſer ſort of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Catholickes then from beleeuing that Councels definition.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:21242:21"/>
            <p>Thus you ſee, how, and why men did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate without a ſeparation then, and why they may not now.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe the Prieſt who anſwered me about praying to Saints, told me that many things in <hi>Rome</hi> are taught, <hi>inter piècredenda,</hi> things to bee religiouſly beleeued. As the Popes power to depoſe Princes, which you ſee is denyed by Prieſts that daily ſay Maſſe, to this day as well learned <hi>French</hi> as <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who call it, <hi>Nonam Catholicam fidem Ieſuitarum:</hi> The Ieſuites new Catholicke Faith. So that this late vp-ſprung error in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> wants not men vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in the ſame Church, to teach truth, and correct error, as in all former ages ſome alwayes haue done.</p>
            <p>So powerfull is God to defend his Church from errors, euen by thoſe that are members of that corrupt part of the Church, according to that ſaying, that there ſhould be <hi>ſome Doctors, ſome Paſtors,</hi> to teach the truth, hee could haue ſaid one Pope, if he had meant ſo.</p>
            <p>It is not amiſſe to haue a little further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of that army of Prieſts, the Ieſuites which attend the Pope, according to the mouthes of their owne Prieſts. <hi>It is obſerued</hi> (ſaith one of them)
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quod. p.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>by men, how religious or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders haue their periods.</hi> And againe,
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 74.</note> 
               <hi>That at the riſing of euery new order, ſome are raiſed vp to be a curbe to that Order.</hi> It being ſo (as
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bagſh. anſ. p.</hi> 8.</note> ſome of the temporall Magiſtrates haue told the Ieſuites) that Ieſuitiſme of a <hi>ſerpigo,</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21242:22"/>a Gangrene, it muſt therefore bee cut off. For
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quodl. p.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 75.</note> 
               <hi>We are perſwaded they will be drawen to ſuch matters, as a Viſum eſt ſpiritui ſanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; nobis,</hi> i.e. (It ſeemeth good to the holy Ghoſt, and to vs) <hi>muſt indicially paſſe indefinitine ſentence againſt them. And the Pope is to be intreated to lay the Axe to the roote of the tree, and to cut off this pride of this ſociety, ſpreading it ſelfe farre and neere, for vnleſſe a damme be ſet vp againſt the ſtreame thereof, the raging courſe will burſt aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all bonds of honeſty and modeſty, and carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way headlong, many with the force therof. It
<note n="e" place="margin">Relat. of the faction at <hi>Wisb. p.</hi> 77.</note> is time to looke to them, for they are become already incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible of any Prince, Prelate or People, and therfore an heauy deſtruction is like to come to their Society, and ſurely their fall without ſpeciall miracle is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable, and they are like enough to be expelled by force. Theſe contentions cannot end but with bloud for as they liue Templar-like in all things, there will be a right Templarian downefall.</hi> And all ought to aſſiſt to the pulling downe of theſe Templarian Ieſuiticall Sectaries, and baniſhing them out of the Chriſtian world. Otherwiſe they will be the meanes to deſtroy all Popes and Kings, and to gouerne with their Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Superior, as you may ſee in the latter end of <hi>Watſons Quodlibets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If out of their owne Prieſts mouthes, they be thus iudged, who are vnder the Popes curſe; What would the ſaid Prieſts ſpeake, if they were free from the ſaid curſe, as the Proteſtants are: I make no doubt but that they would ſay
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21242:22"/>(as the Proteſtants proue) their ſeparation from the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church was moſt lawfull and iuſt, in reſpect of both Prince and State, by reaſon that they are bound to be both Traitors at the Popes will, as appeareth by their doctrines, and alſo Heretickes, if they command it to be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>ex Cathedra.</hi> Both which you may finde to bee vnanſwerably prooued by <hi>T.I.</hi> in his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the holy Catholike Faith and Church ſpecially in his 15 Chapter. I may ſay vnanſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably prooued, becauſe <hi>H. Floyd</hi> the Ieſuite tould me (as I ſaid before) <hi>they muſt be anſwered another way.</hi> Finding (as it ſeemeth) he thought their cauſe weakened by their inſufficient an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres already. Otherwiſe what needed ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny plottes and treaſons as haue beene acted by them, ſince their doctrines teach the ſame <hi>ordine ad deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Spirituale,</hi> in order vnto God and ſpirituall good, as is diſcouered by their owne Prieſts. And doth not <hi>Bellarmine</hi> giue this in reaſon why the Chriſtians in the primitiue times reſiſted not <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Diocleſian, viz: quia deërant vires,</hi> they wanted ſtrength. And doth not <hi>R. Parſon</hi> in his <hi>Andrew Philopater</hi> ſay bouldly that when Kings doe deflect from their Catholike Religion which he meaneth to be the <hi>Romiſh, Liberos eſse ſubditos &amp;c:</hi> That the ſubiects are free from their allegiance <hi>Poſſeque et debere ſi vires habuerint, eiuſmodi hominem è dominatu eijcere</hi> that they may, &amp; ought, if they be able, caſt ſuch a one out of his gouernment.</p>
            <p>If I had not found both by their Doctrine
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21242:23"/>and practiſe that a man could not be a Catholike after the <hi>Roman</hi> faſhion but that he muſt needes be a traytor, in my Conſcience I had not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken them. For I ſhould haue been caried away as the wiſeſt and learnedſt Papiſts are at this day tyed by the Ieſuits <hi>blinde, dead Carbeis obedience</hi> not to ſearch and beleeue what God biddeth but what the Pope and my ghoſtly father teach, hoodwinking and lulling a man a ſleepe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeeing any more, with theſe words <hi>ipſi enim praeuigilabunt quaſi ratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>reddituri pro animabus veſtris</hi> (i.e.) for they watch ouer you as they that ſhall giue account for your ſoules; and <hi>Obedience is better then Sacrifice.</hi> Their meaning is obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Prieſt or Pope, howſoeuer not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you to ſee or vnderſtand thoſe words <hi>Cum docuerint te iuxta legem eius</hi> i.e. when they ſhall teach thee according vnto his law, and forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or not ſuffering you to ſee that it is better to obey Gods Commandements, rather then men Councelling maſſacres and powder plottes.</p>
            <p>If they were ſuffered to ſee theſe true bounds of obedience, they could neuer haue had ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſo wiſe and ſo learned men to vndertake a powder plot, as they haue found. The manifold tranſgreſſions of the rule giuen by the Apoſtle <hi>Ro.</hi> 13.1, 2, 5. (Into all which tranſgreſſions this Doctrine of their abſolute obedience to man doth plunge them) doth leade and draw them as the Philiſtines did Sampſon blindfoulded, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that they had put out his eyes. The Apoſtles
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21242:23"/>Rule is let <hi>let euery man be perſwaded in his owne minde Ro:</hi> 14.5. But aſſuredly thoſe in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der plote were not perſwaded in their owne minde but in their obedience to their ghoſtly Fathers that teach it, <hi>ad bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Spirituale,</hi> for a ſpirituall good. As you haue had it from their owne Prieſts mouthes and pennes. So I end: pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Lord Ieſus Chriſt to preſerue vs all to his ſauing Grace.</p>
            <closer>Deo ſoli ſit Gloria.</closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
